# 大家好 昨天冕上竹鼠托夢給我哦
Hi everyone! Yesterday night, a bamboo rat told me in my dream,
# 它說想吃竹笋啦
that it wants to have bamboo shoots.
# 我們去挖點竹笋回來
So we're gonna get some bamboo shoots now.
# 就是那前面
It's right over there.
# 剛好路過兄弟家
We just pass by our buddy's place.
# 我去兄弟家喝口茶
Let me have a sip of tea there.
# 兄弟
Hey, Bro!
# 我來啦
I'm coming!
# 你看 我這兄弟家住山裡
Look! This buddy is living in the mountain,
# 有雞 有鴨 有鵝
with chickens, ducks and geese,
# 還有羊 (註︰這些羊應該是goat)
and goats too.
# 他才富有哇 (註︰他想說「他才富有，不是我」，但英文似乎沒有類似說法)
It's him who has a fortune.
# 你看 雞 鴨 鵝
Look! Chickens, ducks, geese
# 啥都有
Everything!
# 咩
Meeh~!
# 好多
A lot!
# 好靚
Beautiful!
# 你看 這個小羊
Look! These little goats,
# 好多條哇
a lot of them!
# 看到我來啦 全跑啦
They all run away once they see me coming.
# 好小的
They're really small.
# 咩
Meeh~!
# 要不要去我家
You wanna go home with me?
# 很好玩的哦
There's so much fun!
# 它吃樹葉
They're eating the leaves.
# 這羊吃樹葉的
These goats feed on leaves.
# 好漂亮哦
So pretty!
# 一個都沒挖到
Can't find even one.
# 今年沒笋子 今年
This year, there are hardly any bamboo shoots this year.
# 換一個地方來挖
Let's try another place.
# 哎呀 一個大石頭
Aya! A large piece of rock
# 有一個 有一個
Here's one, here's one.
# 嗯 一個那麼小的
Um! A very small one
# 沒事
Never mind
# 就那麼一點點
Just a tiny little bit
# 一口袋都可以裝得下去
It can even be put into a pocket.
# 啊 沒啦
Ah! That's all!
# 就一個
Just one
# 再挖 裡面有沒有
Dig deeper and see if there's any more inside.
# 它姐姐也挖出來 (???????)
Its sister I'm gonna dig out
# 就挖了一個
We've got just one,
# 一個還被我挖爛啦
the single one. I've damaged it a little though.
# 額 夠啦 剛好有一個笋吃
Eh! Enough! At least we have one bamboo shoot.
# 好香哦
It smells great.
# 回去啦 回去啦
Let's go, let's go!
# 這個竹笋挖回來啦
So we're back with the bamboo shoot.
# 我去找一下哪個竹鼠托夢給我的
Let me find the bamboo rat which went into my dream.
# 把我的老腰都挖痛啦
It hurts my back getting the bamboo shoot for it.
# 挖了一下午就挖了一個
I spent the whole afternoon only to have just one.
# 應該是這隻 托夢給我的
I think it's this one which went into my dream.
# 你看 它好喜歡吃這個竹笋啊
Look! It really loves the bamboo shoot.
# 對呀
Right!
# 這個你吃多啦 不行的
Eating too much of it will be a problem.
# 吃多啦 容易拉稀呀
Eating too much may cause diarrhea.
# 因為這個水分很足
Cuz it's very juicy.
# 況且現在快春天啦
It will also be spring very soon.
# 經常會南風天
And there will always be souther.
# 吃多啦 拉尿會拉很多的
You would pee a lot if you eat too much bamboo shoots.
# 哎呀 整個竹鼠都吊起來啦
Aya! The whole bamboo rat is hanging.
# 好不好吃
Does it taste good?
# 竟然托夢我 想吃竹笋
How dare you come to my dream and ask for bamboo shoots?
# 這樣的 這樣的想法肯定不行的
This idea, this idea will certainly be a problem.
# 因為這個竹鼠哇 千萬不要吃這個
Cuz the bamboo rats should never eat the,
# 多 這個怎麼 竹笋啊
too much, I mean, you know, bamboo shoots.
# 吃多了它容易拉稀
Otherwise it would have a diarrhea.
# 容易拉很多尿 就這樣
It may pee a lot, and you know,
# 尿拉多啦 就容易滋生細菌啊
too much pee may become a breeding ground for the bacteria
# 所以
So...
# 額 給你多吃一點 走
Eh! I'll give you more. Let's go!
# 我們到外面去吃 走
Let's enjoy the bamboo shoot outisde. Let's go!
# 這個竹鼠殺好啦
The bamboo rat has been processed.
# 我把它燒一下(註︰Burn似乎有燒成灰碳的意思，故避用)
Let me torch it.
# 燒一下更漂亮
Torching it makes it prettier,
# 更香
and smell better.
# 用這稻草燒一下
I'll torch it by burning the straw.
# 你看 這個竹鼠燒好啦
Look! The bamboo rat has been torched.
# 黑不溜秋的 燒的
It's as dark as charcoal.
# 刮一下 刮乾淨一點
Scratch it, scratch it to clean it.
# 牙齒不要 你們吃
I don't want the teeth. Leave it to you guys.
# 像這尾巴都燒焦啦
The tails is also burnt.
# 額 給小狗們吃
Eh! Leave it to the doggies.
# 我裝點水 過一下水
I put some water, and boil it in the water.
# 這就樣把水燒開一下
I'll have the water boiled.
# 在這裡
Here
# 把它
Let me,
# 把這個水倒掉
pour the water away.
# 從新放新鮮的水
And replace with fresh water.
# 放那麼多水
This amount of water,
# 就夠啦
should be enough.
# 額 我們拍點生薑下去
Eh! Let's put some smashed ginger.
# 老生薑
Old ginger
# 那個笋嘞
And the bamboo shoot
# 這個竹笋的話 就那麼一點點
We have just a tiny little bit of bamboo shoot here.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 額 再給你吃一點
Eh! Give you a bit more bamboo shoots.
# 我拿幾個香菇來 湊數
I''ll fetch some shiitake mushrooms, to fill up the wok.
# 太少啦 竹鼠內
Here's too few bamboo rat meat.
# 把這個香菇放下去
I put the mushrooms in.
# 你看
Look!
# 竹鼠燜香菇 加竹笋
Bamboo rat shiitake mushrooms stew, with bamboo shoots.
# 這樣燉 燉一個小時就可以啦
Braise it for an hour, and it's done.
# 今天天氣不錯哦
The weather is quite good today.
# 我把那小狗 把它抱下來
Let me get the puppies, and bring them down here.
# 外面的天氣好 你又不下來
The weather is so good outside. Why don't you want to come down?
# 等下有骨頭吃 不要叫
You'll have bones in a while. No yelping!
# 很聽話吧
Good dogs, aren't they?
# 上面有甚好玩啦
Why do you like being up there so much?
# 下面多好玩啊
It's so much fun here.
# 可以走動一下
You can move around here.
# 小黑肚子那麼大啦
Blacky's belly is that big now.
# 又快生啦 這條
She's, she's about to give birth again, this dog.
# 還有一條在這躲著
There's one more puppy hiding itself.
# 狗
Puppy!
# 敢欺負我是吧 讓你欺負我
How dare you bully me. Who asked you to bully me?
# 哇
Wa!
# 這個 好香啊
It's marvelous!
# 真的好香
It's really nice.
# 可以可以可以 開吃開吃
Good, good, good! Meal time, meal time!
# 好香啊 這個香菇
It smells really nice, the mushrooms.
# 胡跃金
Hu Yuejin
# 嗯 這蠻好吃的哦 (註︰將來如果想幫金洋做字幕的話就要想想怎樣Standardize這句)
Um! It tastes rather nice.
# 這個腳爪 哈哈
This is its claw, ha ha!
# 嗯 嘗香菇
Um! Let me try a mushroom.
# 哇 好香啊 這香菇
Wa! It smells really nice, the mushroom.
# 香菇味十足
It's very flavourful.
# 哇 吃塊竹鼠肉
Wa! Let me have a piece of bamboo rat.
# 這個
This is,
# 竹鼠肉
bamboo rat.
# 它這個 有 看 有點肥肉
There, there's, look, there's a bit of fat.
# 其實這個不有[SIC]油膩的
But in fact it's not greasy at all.
# 我一點都 肥肉都不吃的
I don't eat, I don't eat fat at all.
# 吃得不去就沒事
But I have no problems with it.
# 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
The video ends here.
# 要趕緊吃哦
We need to finish it as soon as possible.
# 等下水都馬上就沒有啦
It will be dried very quickly.
The water will be boiled away.